Guide to the Sylvia Law Papers MC.306
New York University Archives
Sylvia Law Papers
1977-2007
New York University Archives
Law, Sylvia A.
MC.306
3.5 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes
Sylvia Law (1942) is an attorney, legal scholar, and the Elizabeth K. Dollard Professor of Law, Medicine, and Psychiatry Emerita at the NYU School of Law. The Sylvia Law Papers (dated 1977-2007) consists of materials relating to Law's professional, scholarly, and teaching career. It includes documentation of court cases and legal campaigns; MacArthur fellowship information; drafts and published articles; press releases and reviews; and correspondence regarding legal causes, writing projects, speaking engagements, and academic life at the School of Law.
Arrangement
The materials in the collection are arranged in a single file listing with all material listed alphabetically by topic.
Biographical Note
Sylvia Law is the Elizabeth K. Dollard Professor of Law, Medicine, and Psychiatry Emerita. She earned her B.A. at Antioch College in 1964 and her J.D. at New York University School of Law in 1968. Law began working at the NYU School of Law in 1973 and over the course of her teaching career, she has taught constitutional law, family law, and health law. She has also participated in the Hays Program Seminar at NYU Law. In addition to teaching at NYU, Law has been a visiting professor at the London School of Economics (1969-1970), Harvard Law School (1984), CUNY Law School at Queens College (1989), Stanford Law School (1996), the University of Hawai'i William S. Richardson School of Law (1999-2000), Temple University Beasley School of Law (2005), and the University of Hawai'i William S. Richardson School of Law & Burns School of Medicine.
Sylvia Law specializes in health; gender and justice; poverty; and constitutional law. She has presented civil rights cases before the U.S. Supreme Court, as well as in federal and lower state courts. She has also testified before Congress and state legislatures on a variety of issues.
In 1983, Law became the first lawyer in the United States to be selected as a MacArthur Fellow, and between 1988-1990, she served as president of the Society of American Law Teachers (SALT). She is the co-director of the Arthur Garfield Hays Program and chair of the Rose Sheinberg Lecture program at NYU School of Law. In 2013, the Sylvia A. Law Fellowship in Economic Justice was created as part of the Hays Civil Liberties Program at NYU Law School.
Over the course of her career, Law has written several books including, Blue Cross: What Went Wrong (1973), Pain and Profit: The Politics of Malpractice (1979), and American Health Law (1990).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in Box 8 relate to resumes; job and fellowship recommendations; and student grades -- all of which fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) and are restricted for 75 years. One folder in Box 8 contains medical information and personal identifying information that is under protected under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA). This information will be restricted for 50 years following the date of death of the individual. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the New York University Archives, (212) 998-2646, university-archives@nyu.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sylvia Law in 2019. The accession number associated with this gift is 2019.031.
Scope and Contents
The Sylvia Law Papers (dated 1977-2007) consists of materials relating to Law's professional, scholarly, and teaching career. The collection includes materials documenting Law's role in legal cases and social movement campaigns; documents outlining her role as a professor at New York University School of Law; legal briefs and research notes; symposium and conference materials; papers related to the MacArthur Fellowship; correspondence, briefs, and research materials related to court cases including Webster v. Reproductive Health Services, Robinson v. Jacksonville Shipyards, and Planned Parenthood v. Casey; and documents describing both Law and NYU's opposition to the 1991 confirmation hearings of Justice Clarence Thomas. Correspondence, press releases, drafts, and reviews of Law's book, Pain and Profit: The Politics of Malpractice (1979) and her article "Rethinking Sex and the Constitution" can be found in the collection.
The collection also contains Law's sabbatical request, which includes an overview of how she was intending to use this time, the type of research she planned to conduct focusing on health care financing in Hawai'i, and her reasons for pursuing this topic.
The majority of this collection consists of correspondence between Law and her colleagues; civil rights, non-profits, nongovernmental organizations (NGOs), and social justice organizations including the Non-Traditional Employment for Women (NEW); faculty and students at the NYU School of Law; Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg; and publishers, journal editors, and writing collaborators. Some correspondence focuses upon the formation and work of the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography; and the formation of the Constitution of Nicaragua and MADRE, a women's rights movement in Nicaragua.
Legal correspondence.; Medical personnel -- Malpractice; Sex work -- legislation & jurisprudence; Constitutional law -- Nicaragua; Medical laws and legislation; Articles.; Research notes.; Press releases.; Memorandums.; Briefs (legal documents); Thomas, Clarence, 1948-; Madre (Organization); Ginsburg, Ruth Bader, 1933-2020; New York University. School of Law; United States. Attorney General's Commission on Pornography; John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation
- Address to the National Association of Women Judges, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "After the Brass Ring: Professional Development and Fulfillment After Tenure", circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American National Biography Entry about Christopher Columbus Langdell, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual Statement of Financial Disclosure [RESTRICTED], 1990 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Application for Sabbatical Leave, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Berkshire Conference, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Blue Cross Blue Shield, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Commencement Address at Antioch College, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Commission on Pornography, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Constitutional Law (NYU Law Class), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Constitutional Roots, Rights, and Responsibilities (Smithsonian Institute Symposium), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1978-2001
  - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 17, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence -- RESTRICTED, 1981-2001
  - 1981 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1986 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1987 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 1991 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 1992 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - 1993 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - 1994 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - 2000 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - 2001 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Correspondence -- About Edward V. Sparer, 1985-1987, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence -- About "Addiction, Autonomy, and Advertising", 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence -- Black Allied Law Students Association (BALSA) and Professor Graham Hughes, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence -- Ginsburg, Ruth Bader, 1983, 1993, 2000, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Court Documents, 1989, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- "The Courts, Politics, and the ACLU", 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Curriculum Vitae, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- "Debate on Welfare and Work", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Dunwoody Lecture, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Eastman, Crystal, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Feminist Legal Strategies Project, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Florida Law Project, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- "The Founding Fathers on Families", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Fox v. Bowen (AALS Poverty Law Section), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Gonzales v. Carhart and Gonzales v. Planned Parenthood, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Historian's Brief - Webster v. Reproductive Health, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Interest on Lawyer Account Fund of the State of New York, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- MacArthur Fellowship, 1982-1983, 1985-1987, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
- "Malpractice -- Is There A Crisis?", 1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Medicare Beneficiaries Defense Fund, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- The New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation (HHC), 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
- New York State Oath of Office Certificate, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Nicaragua, 1985-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Non-Traditional Employment for Women (NEW), 1985-1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- NYU Law School Memoranda, 1985-1994 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Opposition to Confirmation of Judge Clarence Thomas, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Pain and Profit: The Politics of Malpractice, 1977-1979, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
- Pain and Profit: The Politics of Malpractice [RESTRICTED], 1979 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- People of the State of Illinois v. Henrietta Adams, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Pilpel, Harriet, 1991, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Planned Parenthood v. Casey, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Pre-Appointment Financial Questionnaire [RESTRICTED], 1990 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- "President's Message for SALT Equalizer", 1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Research Grant Reports, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Rethinking a National Health Program: Health Care in the Post Reagan Era Conference, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- "Rethinking Sex and the Constitution", 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Robinson v. Jacksonville Shipyards, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Sabbatical and Summer Report, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
- Sex Discrimination Brief, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- The Sex Panic: A Conference on Women, Censorship, and Pornography, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- "Some Reflections on Goldberg v. Kelly at Twenty Years", 1991 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- "Thoughts on the Twentieth Anniversary of Medicaid", 1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Travel Expenses, 1985, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Untitled Essay about American Healthcare Policy, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Untitled Essay for Reader's Companion to U.S. Women's History, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- "Who Will Control Medical Practice in the Year 2000?" (Conference Remarks), 1998 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- "Why Won't Reagan Allow Us to Visit Cuba?", 1984 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Women at NYU Law, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 15)